# 大家好 攝影小哥家的板栗熟了哦
Hi everyone! Mr. Cameraman's chestnuts are now ripe.
# 他叫我過來摘 他摘不到
He asked me to come and pick them, saying that he couldn't.
# 袋子也帶好了啦 這個剪 鉗子我也帶好啦
So I've come, with a bag, and also with these scissors, this pincer.
# 就是天公不作美 下了雨而已
Everything is ready, except that God was not doing us a favour. It rained.
# 這麼簡單的事 他都摘不到 還叫我
It's just a simple task. Why can't he do it himself? Why does he need to ask me?
# 哎呀 這顆大
Aya! This is big!
# 你看 這個漂亮啊
Look! This is pretty.
# 你看 摘了那麼一點 夠了 現在還沒老哦
Look! I've picked just a bit here. It's enough. They are not really that old now.
# 這個只能當水果吃 很嫩的
They can only be eaten as fruits. They're really young.
# 把它裝點回去
I bring them home with this bag.
# 連樹枝也要裝回去
I am taking the branches as well.
# 這樣就不會刺到手
Then they won't sting my hands,
# 因為今天沒做好準備
as I'm not in full gear today.
# 哎呦
Ayo!
# 哎呀 夠了夠了 一米袋
Aya! Enough, enough! A big bag!
# 帶回去剝開
Let's bring them back and peel them.
# 剛好路過兄弟家 你看 他家的雞 一地都是
We just pass by our buddy's place. Look! His chickens, they're everywhere.
# 拉的到處都是雞屎
And they poo at every corner.
# 抓兩個來 剛好晚上沒有 沒有那個菜吃了
Let me catch a couple of them. It just so happens that we've run out, run out of, of food for dinner.
# 你看 好多這個荷苞豆啊
Look! Here are a lot of this kind of runner beans.
# 是我們這邊的豆子 很好吃的哦 這個豆子
These are our local beans here. They taste really good, these beans.
# 用來煲那個豬骨頭 煲湯 特別好吃
It's exceptionally tasty when they're boiled with pork bones, to make a soup.
# 很粉嫩的
It's mushy and tender.
# 你看 這個正宗的土雞
Look! These are authentic free-range chickens.
# 你看 這個板栗 拿回來啦
Look! These chestnuts, are taken back now.
# 直接挖開就行啦 剛好有個銼子
Simply peel them right away and that's it. It just so happens that I have a screwdriver here.
# 就一個 那麼大的苞就一個籽
Just one. It's such a big pack but it has only one chestnut.
# 太小氣了
So mean!
# 你看 這個板栗 剛熟的哦
Look! This chestnut, is newly ripe, you know.
# 還不是很熟 但是特別好吃
It's still not really that ripe. But it's really tasty.
# 這個 這個表面這個衣 挺好的哦
This, this skin on its surface, is rather good, you know.
# 就是粘在這裡 粘在肉上
It's sticking here, sticking on the pulp.
# 你看 把這個它的
Look! After removing,
# 這個衣 把它搞掉的話
it's skin, it's skin here,
# 很好吃的這個 細皮嫩肉的 這個肉 果肉
it's really tasty. It's young, smoother and tender, this pulp, its pulp,
# 板栗肉
chestnut pulp.
# 誒呦 這怎麼跑了一個蟲子出來
Ayo! Why is there a bug coming out from the bag?
# 那麼大的蟲子 嚇我一大跳
Such a big bug. It scared me.
# 你看這蟲子 好大啊這個蟲子
Look! This bug, is really big, this bug.
# 這個板栗剝好了哦 細皮嫩肉的 你看
So I've peeled this chestnut. It's smooth, young and tender. Look!
# 嗯 好香啊
Um! It smells so good!
# 跑到我這裡來幹嘛
Why did you come to my place here?
# 帶你去
Let me take you,
# 放 放歸自然
back, back to the nature.
# 蟲子好像有毛 看到沒有
It seems that there's hair on this bug. See?
# 把它放 放回大自然去吧
Let me release it, release it back to the nature.
# 哪裡來的回哪裡去
Go back to where you came from.
# 去吧 哦
Go, go onward! Oh?
# 沒摔死吧
Did it survive the drop?
# 這個手沒力
This arm is not strong enough.
# 樹上掛著
It's hanging on the tree.
# 這黃的就可以吃啊 黑的就不能吃啊
You can eat these brown ones, but not the black ones, got it?
# 你看 這些嫩嫩的 特別好吃
Look! They're young and tender. Really tasty!
# 這兩塊給你吃
These two are for you.
# 都有點老了
It's a bit old.
# 你看 這兩個鴨子 一個黃的一個白的
Look! These two ducks, one is brown and one is white.
# 不知道怎麼回事
Who knows that happened.
# 殺好啦 把它吹碎來 準備燉
They are ready and cleaned now. I'm gonna chop them into pieces. Then we can stew them,
# 燉點湯
and take a soup.
# 你看 兄弟看到我們買了雞哦
Look! My buddy saw that we've bought chickens.
# 我還隨便帶了幾個靈芝給我們
So he brought us some lingzhi as he passed by.
# 等一下 他說他過來一起吃
He said that he's gonna enjoy with us, in a while.
# 這個是野生的靈芝哦 很漂亮的 一起燉雞
These are wild lingzhi. Really pretty. Let me cook it with the chickens.
# 先把它處理一下
Let me get them ready first.
# 你看 這是靈芝哦 分兩鍋太多了
Look! There are the lingzhi. There are too many. I put them into two pots.
# 這是香菇 笋乾 放在一起
These are shiitake mushrooms, and dried bamboo shoots, putting together.
# 攝影小哥的最愛
Shiitake mushrooms, and dried bamboo shoots,
# 就是香菇笋乾
are Mr. Cameraman's most favourite.
# 還有其他東西 一起混合在一起吃
There's also some other stuff. We mix them up all together.
# 放點生薑
Put some ginger.
# 這個放在這裡
Put it here.
# 哇 你看 蓋起來
Wa! Look! Cover it first!
# 用大火燒它
Cook it on high heat.
# 另外一個的話我那個 用那個煤氣來煲
Well, the other one, I'm gonna boil it with the, you know, with gas.
# 香菇
Mushrooms
# 看這兩隻羊 咩~
Have a look at these two goats! Mehhhh~
# 哎呦 摸都不給我摸一下
Aya! They don't even let me touch them.
# 跑的好快 快一碰到它就跑
They run really fast and run away once I get close.
# 我上去看一下那個豬 看下豬
Let me go up and have a look at the big. See the if the pig,
# 有沒有吃飽
has eaten enough.
# 誒呦 你看你看你看 它還兇我
Aya! Look, look, look! It growls at me.
# 嗯 你看
Um? Look!
# 快點睡下去 睡下去睡下去 快點
C'mon! Lie down! Lie down, lie down! C'mon!
# 它不睡
It doesn't want to.
# 好警愓啊 你看 睡不去啊 是不是
It's on high alert. Look! It lies down now, right?
# 睡下去
Lie down.
# 這是公的哦 這個
It is male, this pig.
# 不配合
It's not cooperating with me.
# 它的毛怎麼堅起來了
Why is its hair standing up?
# 你看 搞的一身都是泥巴 現在都好像胖了一點
Look! It's covered with mud. It seems that it has become a bit fatter now.
# 它很聽明的哦 身上有泥巴 蚊子就咬不到它
It's really clever. This mosquitoes can't sting it when it's covered with mud.
# 豬頭
Pig head
# 豬頭豬腦
Pig head with a pig brain
# 它吃飽了現在
Now it has eaten enough.
# 我看一下我的燙 別燒糊了
Let me have a look at my soup. Don't let it get burnt.
# 你看這個羊 它在懸崖消壁上隨便走動的哦
Have a look at this goats. They can run around freely on the cliffs, you know.
# 一點事都沒有 吃的好飽啊現在 這羊都很漂亮啦
It won't bother them at all. They have now a lot of food. These goats are so pretty now.
# 下來下來
Come down, come down!
# 過來
Come here!
# 咩~
Mehhh~
Mehhh!
# 過來
Come here!
# 捉都捉到它們了
I can't even catch them now.
# 加點鹽
Put some salt.
# 這筷子是沒吃的
These chopsticks have not yet been used.
# 還沒開始吃
We've not yet started.
# 應該差不多了
It should be alright now.
# 搞個雞腿吃一下
Let me get a chicken leg and have a try.
# 嗯 好吃
Um! Tasty!
# 你看 放了靈芝 好鮮甜啊 這個雞
Look! With some lingzhi, it's savoury sweet, this chicken.
# 全是瘦肉 一點肥肉都沒有 連油都沒有的
There is only lean meat, not even a bit fat. There's no oil in the soup at all.
# 現在豬肉好貴啊 所以現在我們
Now the price of pork is rocket high. So we now,
# 就買 買雞來吃
we buy, buy chicken instead.
# 來吃它的心肝
Let me eat its heart.
# 這補鐵
It's a good source of iron.
# 哎呦 好燙
Ayo! So hot!
# 你看 全部小狗都過來啦
Look! All the doggies are around me now.
# 搞快點 給骨頭給它們吃
Let me get them a piece, a piece of bone.
# 哇 這個雞湯好喝的 這雞湯 你看
Wa! This chicken soup is really tasty, this chicken soup. Look!
# 太燙啦 用那個冷的碗 攪拌一下
It's too hot. So I put it into this cold bowl, and stir it for a while.
# 這個燙 等一下就涼啦
The soups, it cools down right away.
# 啊~
Ah~
# 啊~好吃
Ah~ Tasty!
# 好啦 今天的視頻到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 家人都回來啦 全部一起來吃 (註︰翻譯配合他的語氣)
Our wives and children are all back here. Let's have a big feast.
# 趁現在放暑假 大家都回來啦
During the summer holidays, when everybody is back,
# 多搞點好吃的給它們吃
I wanna treat them with more good food.